

Personal information

Name Martina Ilarri

Birthdate December 29, 1981

Gender Female

Residence Portugal

Nationality Brazilian/Śpanish/Portuguese

Scientific profile

- **CIENCIA ID** E212-E1D1-4509
- **Scopus author ID** 16426031100
- **ORCID** 0000-0001-6780-8221

ResearchGate

https://www.researchgat e.net/profile/Martina-Ilarri

Scientific metrics

Peer-reviewed papers



37 (Scopus) 39 (ResearchGate)

H-index



15 (Scopus) 17 (ResearchGate)

Total citations Research fields

- **Biological invasions**
- Aquatic ecology
- **Climate change**
- Conservation

MARTINA ILARRI

RESEARCHER

I obtained a European PhD in Marine and Environmental Sciences from the University of Porto (Portugal) in 2012 and have been involved in ecological studies of estuarine and freshwater fauna since 2001. During my career, I have actively collaborated with more than 50 researchers, published 37 scientific papers in peer-reviewed journals, and given more than 50 presentations at national and international conferences. I am a member of the editorial board of a journal and I have worked as a reviewer for 10 different journals. I have actively participated in eight scientific projects and received individual grants within the framework of 4 open calls. I have also given some selected lectures at university level in Portugal. I have a strong interest in environmental data, and in contributing to the advancement of scientific knowledge to improve our understanding of nature and the conservation of biodiversity.

Experience

Researcher

CIIMAR - Interdisciplinary Centre of Marine and Environmental Research of t he University of Porto, Portugal | 2018 - Present

Post-doctoral fellow

Foundation for Science and Technology - FCT, Portugal | 2013 - 2018

Education

Master/Data Science University of Porto, Porto | 2021 - Present

PHD/Doctoral School in Marine and Environmental Sciences

University of Porto, Portugal | 2008 - 2012

Thesis: Functional importance of the Asian clam Corbicula fluminea in invaded ecosystems

Master/Biological Sciences - Zoology

Universidade Federal da Paraiba, Brazil | 2006 - 2008

Thesis: The study of the fish assemblage of full protection areas in comparison to the fish assemblage of sustainable use areas, at the archipelago of Fernando de Noronha - PE, Southwestern Atlantic.

Bachelor/Biological Sciences - Marine Biology Universidade Federal Fluminense, Brazil | 2000 - 2005

Thesis: The effect of nutrients enrichment on the development of marine biofauling communities with the absence of predators.

Skills

R software

Data analysis (frequentist statistic) Data processing (structured data) Data management

Programming languages

Git

Languages

Portuguese English Spanish German

Selected first author publications

Dataset

Long-term monitoring of the fish community in the Minho **Estuary (NW Iberian Peninsula)**

Souza et al., Zenodo (doi: https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8046541) | 2023

Article

Influence of climate change and extreme weather events on an estuarine fish community

Ilarri & Souza et al., Science of the Total Environment | 2022

Spatio-temporal and intra-specific variations in the physiological and biochemical condition of the invasive bivalve Corbicula fluminea

Ilarri et al., Hydrobiologia | 2022

Decay and persistence of empty bivalve shells in a temperate riverine system

Ilarri et al., Science of the Total Environment | 2019

Physical legacy of freshwater bivalves: Effects of habitat complexity on the taxonomical and functional diversity of invertebrates

Ilarri et al., Science of the Total Environment | 2018

Community structure of reef fishes in shallow waters of the Fernando de Noronha archipelago: Effects of different levels of environmental protection

Ilarri et al., Marine and Freshwater Research, | 2017

Teaching

University of Minho, Portugal



Master's level: Invited lectures on sampling data in tropical aquatic environments.

2011

University of Minho, Portugal



Master's level: Invited lectures on Multivariate analysis applied to ecological data.

2015

Supervisions



PhD Sudents

Co-supervisor of 1 PhD student in the University of Minho (Portugal)

Master Students



Supervisor of 4, and co-supervisor of 1, MSc students in the University of Minho (Portugal)

Bachelor Students



Supervisor of 2, and co-supervisor of one, BSc students in the Unioversity of Porto (Portugal)

Editorial services



Recent activities

Course - Ready for BioData Management? CIIMAR Porto, Portugal - Januray, 2023

COST Action - Conservation of freshwater mussels: a pan-

European approach Training school on Freshwater mussel ecosystem services Prague, Czechia - September of 2021

Master in Data science, Faculty of Science, University of Porto Porto, Portugal - Started in October of 2020 - ongoing

The IUCN EICAT system and its application Workshop - Taller de formación: "El sistema EICAT de la UICN y su aplicacion"

Merida, Spain - September of 2018

References

Allan Souza

Researcher Institute of Hydrobiology, Biology Centre, CAS, Czechia allantsouza@gmail.com

Ronaldo Sousa

Professor (PhD Supervisor) Department of Biology, University of Minho, Portugal rg.eco.sousa@gmail.com

Contact

- Rua Dom António Barroso, 213, 4° Dto, 4050-060, Porto, Portugal
- **1** +351 936393982
- martinailarri@gmail.com
- s martina_ilarri